earlier today Conrad black wrote an
article in Canada's National Post and
the article was called Jordan Peterson
speaks for those of us who refused to
follow the great liberal death wish now
for those of you who don't know who
Conrad Black is I'll read you a little
bit from his wikipedia profile Conrad
Moffitt black baron black of cross
Harbor was born on the 25th of August
1944 he's a Canadian born British former
newspaper publisher and author he's a
non-affiliated life pierre black
controlled Hollinger international once
the world's third largest
english-language newspaper Empire which
published the Daily Telegraph in the UK
the Chicago sun-times in the US and the
Jerusalem Post Israel as well as in the
National Post the newspaper that he
published this article in in Canada and
hundreds of community newspapers in
North America I'd like to start this by
thanking Lord black for his support but
I would also like to point out that
despite his supportive stance there are
things that are important that he didn't
get right and I think it's reasonable to
draw people's attention to them so the
first thing I'm going to do is just read
what he wrote and then I'm going to
comment on it a little bit and I'm going
to do so in a manner that I hope does
indicate that I do appreciate his
support and I'm not trying to be
frivolously critical in any sense and
then I want to read a response that a
lawyer has prepared as well just so that
you understand all of you who are
listening understand this a little bit
more clearly
Conrad black writes I have just endured
the sobering experience of watching the
always very intelligent and professional
Steve Paikin chair a panel about the
transgender controversy that centers on
University of Toronto professor dr.
Jordan Peterson that was the I had an
appearance on TV I was the agenda with
Steve Paikin a couple of weeks ago where
the pronoun issue was discussed black
states I have a
we followed the story as it percolated
up in the press much of the fraud things
in which must usually be taken lightly
it was I fear a piercing glimpse into
what great and venerable statesmen of my
youth such as Winston Churchill Dwight
Eisenhower Harry Truman and Louis a law
called days that I shall not see I did
not until now grasp the fine balance
between gratitude and wistfulness in
their invocation of that phrase as a
young person I thought at the license of
the great to engage in histrionics and I
now claim it as the right of lesser yet
aging people such as myself black States
for those who have sagely ducked or
otherwise being spared exposure to this
controversy dr. Peterson rejects the
right of his students to require him to
address them if they are trans people ie
in some state of flux between the male
and female poles of gender
identification not their orientation
whether they are homosexual heterosexual
bisexual or asexual has nothing to do
with it otherwise then in a way that
consigns them to the Kloster confines of
being male or female no see this is one
of the things that's interesting about
about mr. blacks call him he obviously
considers this issue of sufficient
importance to address it but there's an
that he can't eliminate completely from
his mind this supposition that this is
absurd but and it is absurd in many ways
but here's the mistake just because
something is absurd doesn't mean it was
it's trivial and I think this is where
mr. black makes an error in his column
yes it's absurd that's why he says it
that people have sagely ducked it or
otherwise being spared exposure to it
because it's been a ridiculous
controversy and I think I think there's
no question about that it's surreal I
found the whole thing surreal but you
know back in the 1930s when the Nazis
first made their appearance on the scene
everyone thought they were observed -
and and concluded that that meant that
they were trivial and they were not
trivial despite their absurdity and this
is not trivial despite its absurdity in
fact its absurdity I think in some sense
points precisely to the fact that it is
anything but trivial because something
that is on the surface of it so absurd
is being made
and so much as being made of it it's
being classified the reviews will use
pronouns for example is being classified
as a hate crime
that's not trivial although it is absurd
now Z for he and or she and xur in place
of his or him are the sticking points
but what is accumulating behind these
imbecilic distinctions is quite sinister
the tape Steve Paikin ran up dr.
Peterson being reviled and shouted down
and physically intimidated at the
University of Toronto was distressing
and we may be on the edge of a defining
moment in our jolly and progressive
Canadian civilization dr. Peterson sees
it as a matter of freedom of expression
and believes that others do not have the
authority to require him to address them
in a newly hatched vocabulary devised to
oppress the quote gender binary
conventional practice while his
opponents professed to believe that in
refusing to do so he is committing a
hate crime punishable by Human Rights
Commission's or tribunals these hoary
headed monsters and black is referring
to the human rights tribunals whose
egregious trespasses on freedom of
expression in the name of despotic
political correctness has been heroic
being successfully contested by my
friends mark Stein and Ezra Levant and
others does not prescribe imprisonment
under the Articles invoked by dr.
Peterson's assailants but a fine is
possible yes and we might also point out
that it's a very large fine that is
possible in New York State for example
failure to use the requisite pronouns
brings with it a maximum fine of two
hundred and fifty thousand dollars in
any case Conrad goes on to say as if to
assure the least possibility of a quiet
end to this preposterous issue dr.
Peterson has declared that he will not
pay a fine and if imprisoned for not
paying it would embark on a hunger
strike now this is another place where
black confuses absurdity with triviality
he believes that my response to this is
an overreaction and that's part of my
refusal to bring this preposterous issue
to a quiet end he's he's suggesting that
I'm exaggerating and that as a
consequence he's implying that I'm at
least in part responsible for blowing up
something that's merely absurd into
something
I'm blowing up the importance of
something that's merely absurd anyways
he says while my sympathies are with dr.
Peterson this is an unjustified
hypothetical escalation to remember that
he says this is an unjustified
hypothetical escalation if it came to
that the authorities would attach his
bank account or is income and collect
the fine in that manner rather than
imprisoning him and provoking a hunger
strike yes well we'll see about that
okay so the first thing that I want to
tell you listeners is here's here's the
powers of the social justice tribunals I
pulled this from their own statement
about their power so this is one point
six this is section one point six powers
of this social justice tribunals in in
the relevant Ontario legislative
document one point six you have to
listen to this very carefully the
tribunal will determine how a matter
will be dealt with that's a matter
brought before them say a matter of
discrimination or harassment defined by
their policies their appalling policies
and may use procedures other than
traditional adjudicative or adversarial
procedures okay so I'm going to repeat
that the tribunal will determine how a
matter will be dealt with and may use
procedures other than traditional
adjudicative or adversarial procedures
okay that's 1.6 1.7 in order to provide
for the fair just and expeditious
resolution of any matter before it the
tribunal may a limit the evidence or
submissions on any issue so you can
consider that for awhile and I'm going
to skip 2w take any other action that
the tribunal determines is appropriate
now you you've got that they've actually
written a clause into the policy
documents that describe their powers
that states they can take any other
action they determine as appropriate
well then I would say that's gone beyond
absurd or I would say that's still
absurd but it's by no means trivial and
my sense that this is extraordinarily
dangerous legislation is correct whereas
dark mr. blacks insistence that I'm
exaggerating the seriousness of the
situation is incorrect
here's 3.13 from the same document where
a party has been notified of a fair
hearing and fails to attend
the tribunal may II take any other
action it considers appropriate so
that's a duplication of the previous
statement roughly speaking with where
the Human Rights Tribunal takes to
itself the power to do whatever it wants
fundamentally now there are some other
things to consider notice that these
tribunals including the Ontario Human
Rights tribunals there's eight different
tribunals they're called social justice
tribunals now that's not an accident
consider what that means the term social
justice is a code for political
correctness and equity oriented
political philosophy people know that
this is why the radical left activists
are parodied as social justice warriors
now the social justice tribunal is
operating in Ontario or quasi-judicial
instantiations of the politically
correct authoritarian Creed and they're
designed by their designers to operate
outside of the normal parameters of the
law this is why they attribute to
themselves the powers to use quote
procedures other than traditional
adjudicative or adversarial procedures
think about that it means that the
standard British common law approach to
the issues brought before the tribunal
can be suspended now why would they do
that
well it's rooted in politically correct
the underlying politically correct
marxist and post modernist philosophy oh
you can consider it this way if the
fundamental presupposition is that the
that Canadian civilization as well as
Western civilization in general is a
corrupt patriarchy then what's the
problem with suspending its rules of
procedure when you're pursuing a justice
that's higher than anything that's
represented inside that tradition well
that's exactly what they've written into
though into the laws attributing to
themselves power so you can you can
think for yourself and decide just
exactly how dangerous that is now back
to black dr. Peterson's approach is so
inflexible and so entirely righteous
without much using the powerful weapon
of ridicule that is available to him he
may not have tracked the full range of
support the virtue of his arguments and
his personal courage deserve it's a
funny sentence because I can't tell
exactly I get that the terminology
that my approach is so inflexible that I
may not attract the full range of
support the virtue of my arguments my
personal courage deserve I don't really
think that I'm being reflect inflexible
I'm merely refusing to use the language
that's made up by politically correct
radical left-wing authoritarians and
that's not inflexible it's reasonable
why would I use that language I don't
agree with the philosophy I think the
principles upon which it's predicated
are not only factually incorrect
scientifically incorrect but
malevolently motivated and
extraordinarily dangerous that doesn't
make me inflexible and so the
terminology there is wrong
it makes me committed to not using that
language but on the substance of the
issue
Locke continues he is of course correct
we must always be wary of the
majoritarian tyranny which has
preoccupied many civil libertarians
including the principle authors of the
Constitution of the United States
especially James Madison and Alexander
Hamilton who agreed on little else but
the transgender community is less than
1% of the population as I have written
many times in many contexts over many
tears rights do not exist only for the
numerous and a litmus test of legitimacy
of a society is its observance of the
rights of minorities including
especially minorities of one the
jurisprudence of all great democratic
nations is replete with famous cases to
this effect captain Dreyfus dr. Samuel
Mudd who was prosecuted for treating the
assassin of Abraham Lincoln though there
was no evidence that he was involved in
the plot and even the British Archer she
affair made famous in the drama the
Winslow boy the Peterson affair is
threatening to cross the double white
line all people must be treated with
respect equally but there are only two
genders two sexes or species and all
other mammals are gender binary well I
would like to point out to mr. black
that that's now illegal under Bill c16
and its associated sister legislation
and that might be observed as I
mentioned before but it's not trivial
idiocy written into the law unfolds into
the idiocy of enforcement and obedience
and that's not trivial and as we will
soon find out
Locke continues all people may state
their sex and if that is contra
physical appearances that remains there
right but no individual or group has the
right to invent a new vocabulary and a
new cool coequal gender because of a
state of ambivalence or confusion about
which sex they are yes mister black they
do have that right and that's precisely
what bill c16 instantiates and it's
already written into the human right
codes human rights codes of the majority
of Canadian provinces it's also it's
also an act of hate speech to dispute it
so individuals and groups have precisely
the right to invent new vocabularies and
not one but many co-equal genders up to
70 in New York State for example black
continues every legally competent
individual has a perfect and absolute
right to declare their sex but not to
create a new legal status and legally
require the use of a new vocabulary for
those in flux between the only two sexes
we have mercilessly binary Thoreau
they're finite number maybe well the
same argument applies there they do have
the right to create a new legal status
or many new legal status and to legally
require the use of a new vocabulary
written into the law they have that
right and I would say as well that
corner of Black's comments on that are
also now illegal the individuals in that
condition may change the registered sex
each day if they wish but not treat
anyone who declines to address them in
terms that debunk the gender binary
world has guilty of a hate crime
punishable by imposable fines about six
months ago I wrote a column in this
space about the acceptance by the
Supreme Court of Canada to hear an
appeal of judgments from well reasoned
local courts a request from a British
Columbia band of native people numbering
900 who claimed that 25 years of
consultation was constitutionally
inadequate over a proposed ski area that
an elder of their band was
supernaturally advised and after a lapse
of some years told his people would
drive off the spirit of the grizzly bear
that was central to the religion of that
band I concluded the column with the
shabby polemical device that I only
rarely employ a rhetorical question
in this case are we all mad of course we
are not and we still live in a country
where people can self-identify as they
wish even if it diverges from apparent
realities but we were almost at the
point where people who declined to be
legally forced to acknowledge the more
implausible applications of this right
are subject to persecution by social
justice warriors and quite conceivably
the government we're not almost at the
point mr. black it's already written
into law we were terribly finally
reluctant to impose normal rules of free
discourse over the agitations of people
who are using an imagined unlimited
latitude on sexual self-description to
gag dictate to and prosecute reasonable
people exercising the rights to free
expression it is another manifestation
parentheses of which the hyper
hypocritically respectful lamentations
about the Stalinist despot Fidel Castro
or another end parenthesis of what my
late friend Malcolm Muggeridge called
the great liberal Deathwish the great
majority do not want to go long for that
ride and this time the great majority
must be heard and obeyed all right so I
told you what I thought about mr. blacks
comments and and now I'm going to read a
legal opinion about them mr. black I
regularly read your articles with
interest I have interest in many of the
subjects that you seem to devote
attention to including US history and
presidential politics and behavior I
further enjoyed your recent appearances
on CNN with respect respect to the Trump
phenomenon I was motivated to write to
you in this instance with respect to
your article in the National Post today
mentioned in the subject line of this
email a right not to detract from your
main thesis regarding mr. Peterson and
those aligned against him but rather to
identify a potentially missed point of
importance in your article you call into
question the volume of mr. Peterson's
rhetoric my words not yours as being
disproportionate by identifying that
imprisonment is not the punishment that
he faces by disregarding the
gender-neutral ideology and any
resultant orders from a humans rights
tribunal
well you may be and hopefully are
correct that imprisonment is not in mr.
Peterson's future the path to prison
remains clear the key point being that
the human rights tribunals can and
regularly do order non-monetary remedies
in addition to the typical and
well-known monetary awards
well failure to pay a financial penalty
can result in imprisonment it is
admittedly a long and winding road not
entirely related to the unpaid penalty
itself that being said if a tribunal
were to issue its
standard order it would necessarily
include some variation of the following
number one a declaratory order requiring
mr. Peterson not to miss gender someone
again or use the wrong pronouns number
two a gag order requiring him to refrain
from discussing the subject in public
possible given his academic status
number three a publication ban requiring
him to refrain from publishing on these
subjects possible given his media
presence and number four to take
mandatory sensitivity or anti bias
training if mr. Peterson were to breach
these orders for example by refusing to
participate in the training and guess
what I would do the typical recourse of
the tribunal is to pursue a contempt of
court which inevitably results in prison
section 19 of the statutory powers
procedures act Ontario states that an
order of the tribunal is an order of the
Superior Court section 13 of the
statutory powers procedures Act says the
tribunal can pursue a breach of its own
order by bringing an application to the
divisional Court Superior Court on that
application the divisional Court employs
rule 60.1 one of the rules of civil
procedure but states that when faced
with contempt of a non-monetary order of
the Superior Court the court can order
imprisonment for an indefinite period
and fines the civil court's send people
to prison for breaches of non-monetary
injunctions non defamation orders with
some regularity furthermore human rights
tribunals have a history of imprisoning
persons for breaches of non-monetary
monetary tribunal orders this happened
most notoriously under the recently
repealed section 13 hate speech
provisions of the Canadian Human Rights
Code of which mr. Levante and mr. Stein
quietly performed yeoman service for all
Canadian citizens in having repealed
well the likelihood of prison remains
highly contingent and remote it does
depend to a great extent on the
benevolence of the public servants that
staff the tribunal and the courts keep
up the good work D Jarrod Brown lead
counsel D Jared brown proportionate
professional corporation Toronto Ontario
WWE
law dot CA well so there you have it
that's the pathway to imprisonment for
failure to use the proper pronouns and
so let's not be confusing absurdity with
triviality and I appreciate your support
mr. block but um I'm afraid that you're
treating that this issue in some regard
as if it's if it as if at least elements
of it are beneath contempt and that it's
being blowing blown out of proportion
and I'd like to say as clearly as I
possibly can this is not being blown out
of proportion this is the state of
current state of Canadian law